בוקר טוב. Boker tov. How are?
18th day of the עומר. Omer. We pick up דף, daf, today's
דף daf is י"ב. Yud Bet. We pick up the bottom of
י"א עמוד ב' Yud Aleph Amud Bet on the משנה. Mishna. And
we are dealing with things that
there's no מעילה Me'ila for and we had discussed previously in particular
the הלכה halacha about חטאת המצורע Chatas HaMetzora which is different than
something פסול. Passul. We've learned at the beginning of the פרק Perek
that if something becomes פסול Passul it retains מעילה, Me'ila, but חטאת
המצורע Chatas HaMetzora which is going לאיבוד l'ibud is not. And then
we had some other interesting discussions particularly about the idea that blood
is there's a פסוק pasuk that teaches us that although you might
have thought it's the prime thing that there's מעילה Me'ila for in
the קרבן, korban, there's no מעילה Me'ila for blood only after זריקה
zrika and then only דרבנן. D'rabbanan. Okay, now we continue with this
theme. So the משנה Mishna at the bottom of י"א עמוד ב':
Yud Aleph Amud Bet: דשן מזבח הפנימי והמנורה לא נהנין ולא מועלין.
Deshen Mizbe'ach HaPnimi VeHaMenora lo nehenin velo mo'alin. So we had been
discussing in the גמרא Gemara the דשן, deshen, the cleaning of the
ashes from the outer מזבח. Mizbe'ach. And there the question is at
what stage do the ashes that are left that are in the
תפוח Tapuach in the big ash heap to what degree at what
stage is there not מעילה Me'ila for there? After the תרומת הדשן
Terumas HaDeshen or maybe only after they're taken outside. Here we're dealing
with the ashes that are from the מנורה, Menora, that are from
you know within the היכל Heichal which are either the מנורה Menora
or the inner מזבח, Mizbe'ach, the gold מזבח Mizbe'ach in which they
would burn the קטורת, Ketoret, the incense. So they would that also
created ashes, so you would clean that up. So there לא נהנין
ולא מועלין. lo nehenin velo mo'alin. You can't rabbinically you can't derive
הנאה. hana'ah. לא נהנין lo nehenin is always rabbinic but דאורייתא D'oreita
there is no מעילה. Me'ila. Why not? Presumably based on the principle
of נעשה מצוותו, Na'asa Mitzvato, that you know once the candle has
burned once the מנורה Menora the lights have burned or once the
קטורת Ketoret has been burned, the מצווה mitzvah is already done. Now
the גמרא Gemara interestingly I'll just say does not explore what exactly
is the stage of נעשה מצוותו. Na'asa Mitzvato. Again by the outer
מזבח Mizbe'ach the question is is it after the תרומת הדשן, Terumas
HaDeshen, after they're fully removed. Here it doesn't explore. תוספות Tosafot brings
another גמרא Gemara that makes it clear that by the קטורת Ketoret
it's once the the pillar of incense of the the aroma the
smoke starts rising up from the קטורת. Ketoret. So similar to what
the גמרא Gemara said about the אימורין emurim of קדשים קלים, Kodshim
Kalim, that as soon as basically they start burning. And it's a
little funny that why is that different than the other ashes? And
I'll just remind us again a point that תוספות Tosafot made, that
תוספות Tosafot basically said that the מצווה mitzvah that we read in
the beginning of צו Tzav that there's a מצווה mitzvah of תרומת
הדשן Terumas HaDeshen or that there's a מצווה mitzvah of removing the
ashes, that's number one only on the outer מזבח Mizbe'ach and as
תוספות Tosafot says it's number one only by עולה Olah or maybe
קדשי קדשים. Kodshei Kodshim. So other things where there's not a specific
מצווה mitzvah of תרומת הדשן Terumas HaDeshen or the or even more
of removing the ashes, the מצווה mitzvah is not done with the
ashes the מצווה mitzvah is done to the object that was burning
and that's done as soon as the object basically starts burning. Okay,
so the so that the discussions we had before that it required
תרומת הדשן Terumas HaDeshen or required removal that was only by the
outer מזבח Mizbe'ach by the קדשי קדשים Kodshei Kodshim where there's a
מצווה mitzvah of that. Here once it's already started burning there's no
longer its מצווה mitzvah is done and therefore there's no longer מעילה.
Me'ila. So that's דשן מזבח הפנימי והמנורה. Deshen Mizbe'ach HaPnimi VeHaMenora. Then
it goes on and I know that was a lot to read
that one line of the משנה Mishna but there's no גמרא Gemara
there's very little גמרא Gemara on it and for my sake anyway
I wanted to position it relative to the other ashes discussion and
here the basic point as I said is the other ashes discussion
because there's a מצווה mitzvah in the beginning of צו Tzav of
removal of the ashes and that postpones the נעשה מצוותו Na'asa Mitzvato
stage. Here where there isn't one as soon as it becomes ashes
or even earlier it's נעשה מצוותו. Na'asa Mitzvato. That's the that's the
ashes.
Then המקדיש דשן בתחילה מועלין בו. HaMakdish deshen batichla mo'alin bo. Somebody
just sanctifies ashes, there is מעילה Me'ila by ashes. Now what does
that mean? So the רמב"ם, Rambam, you know רש"י Rashi and תוספות
Tosafot basically think that that's you know doesn't can't just mean that
if you sanctify ashes there's מעילה Me'ila that's obvious. So they try
to explain it in the context of the removal of the ashes
from the מקדש Mikdash that somehow if you re-sanctify it there can
also be מעילה Me'ila even after it's been burned. But again that's
it's very complicated and I'll just tell you the רמב"ם Rambam reads
it very simply: it just says look it tells you that no
matter how trivial you think it is the thing that you're sanctifying,
if you sanctify a pile of dung, you could sanctify ashes, there
still is מעילה. Me'ila. And that's all it's saying we're talking about
ashes so it's saying if you sanctify ashes there's מעילה. Me'ila. Fine.
Now we get to now we get to the point that we
discussed yesterday which will carry on to the next משנה: Mishna: תורין
שלא הגיע זמנם ובני יונה
שעבר זמנם. Torin shelo higia zmanan uvnei yona she’avar zmanan. If you
have these pigeons and turtle doves, so the תור Tor has to
be an adult and it's not yet an adult when you sanctify
it, or a בן יונה ben yona this you're sanctifying it as
a קרבן korban has to be a under age a child as
it were and it's and it's too old שעבר זמנם she'avar zmanan
now it's too old. לא נהנין ולא מועלין. lo nehenin velo mo'alin.
You sanctify it there is you can't derive benefit but there's no
מעילה Me'ila and again we'll discuss in the גמרא Gemara why not
since anyway a קרבן korban that's פסול passul there certainly is מעילה,
Me'ila, why is
this different? It's מוסב musav like this: בשלמא מזבח החיצון, bishlama mizbe'ach
hachitzon, I understand the outer מזבח, mizbe'ach, דכתיב ביה dechitiv bei ושמו
אצל המזבח. vesamo etzel hamizbe'ach. You put the ashes by the side
of the
מזבח. mizbe'ach. מזבח הפנימי מנלן? mizbe'ach hapnimi minalan? Where do I know
the inner מזבח? mizbe'ach? Now what do I know it for what
הלכה? halacha? So there's a long תוספות Tosafos because it doesn't really
seem like what the גמרא Gemara is doing is discussing the משנה,
mishna, I gave you the relevant discussion of the משנה, mishna, when
is it נעשה מצותו. naaseh mitzvaso. So תוספות Tosafos really says all
the גמרא Gemara's trying to figure out is since the משנה mishna
says the דישון המזבח, dishun hamizbe'ach, the removal of ashes, and it
doesn't tell you what you do with those ashes from the inner
מזבח mizbe'ach or the מנורה, menorah, somehow it's somehow assumed or the
גמרא Gemara's assumed that you do with those ashes what you do
with other ashes like the outer מזבח mizbe'ach and there's an idea
of placing them by the side of the מזבח. mizbe'ach. So that's
not in the משנה, mishna, but the גמרא Gemara somehow assumes that
and that's what it's asking, where do you get this idea that
what you do with the ashes
from the מנורה menorah and from the inner מזבח mizbe'ach is to
put it by the side of the outer מזבח? mizbe'ach? Again, wasn't
in the משנה, mishna, but the גמרא Gemara's somehow assuming that and
then it's asking where you know that from. So it says so
by the outer מזבח mizbe'ach it says ושמו אצל המזבח. vesamo etzel
hamizbe'ach. מזבח הפנימי מנלן? mizbe'ach hapnimi minalan? Where do you know the
same thing you do with the ashes of the inner מזבח? mizbe'ach?
So אמר רבי אלעזר אמר קרא, amar Rabi Elazar amar kra, the
פסוק pasuk says והסיר מראתו בנצתה, vehesir muraso benotzasa,
this is by עולת העוף, olat ha'of,
and it says
והשליך אתה אצל המזבח קדמה אל מקום הדשן, vehishlicho etzel hamizbe'ach kedma
el mekom hadashen,
and you throw it by you throw it to the east of
the altar to the same place you would put the ashes. So
when a person's bringing this קרבן, korban, this bird קרבן, korban, he
throws the innards and it goes to the place of the ashes
at the side of the ramp to the מזבח. mizbe'ach. So אם
אינו ענין למזבח החיצון, im eino inyan lemizbe'ach hachitzon,
now it didn't have to say that. Now the question is why
didn't it have to say that? We'll talk in a minute. Somehow
that wasn't needed for the outer מזבח mizbe'ach because we know the
outer מזבח mizbe'ach where the ashes go and somehow we would by
the case of the innards of this bird we would have known
it so it's seen as an extra פסוק. pasuk. תניהו ענין למזבח
הפנימי, tneihu inyan lemizbe'ach hapnimi, it's coming to tell you that the
idea that you place the ashes at the place that there's a
that this is the place you put things, the place where the
ashes go, so the same way this is true about the innards
of this bird, it's also true about the ashes of the inner
מזבח mizbe'ach that they go by the same place the ashes of
the outer מזבח mizbe'ach go at the side of the ramp. So
the גמרא Gemara says אימא אידי ואידי במזבח החיצון ולקבוע לו מקום.
eima eidi ve'eidi bemizbe'ach hachitzon ulekvo'a lo makom. How do you get
how do you know that this פסוק pasuk is extra? Maybe this
פסוק pasuk is telling you that we're talking about why the פשט,
pshat, the outer מזבח, mizbe'ach, and it's telling you that the innards
of the bird have to go exactly in this place, meaning okay
you normally know where the ashes of the מזבח mizbe'ach go, but
this telling you where the innards of the bird go and maybe
it's there to tell you exactly what the place is, it's not
an extra פסוק. pasuk. So the גמרא Gemara says no, אם כן
לימא קרא, im ken leima kra, the פסוק pasuk could say אצל,
etzel, now some add the word אצל etzel again, אצל אצל המזבח,
etzel etzel hamizbe'ach, because it says it could have made a גזירה
שוה. gezeira shava. What does it say by the תרומת הדשן? trumas
hadashen? It says do you have a חומש Chumash here somewhere?
No.
So by the תרומת הדשן trumas hadashen it says
beginning of צו, Tzav,
actually the גמרא Gemara just quoted it ושמו אצל המזבח. vesamo etzel
hamizbe'ach. Let's get the whole פסוק. pasuk. ולבש הכהן
מדו בד ומכנסי בד ילבש על
בשרו והרים את הדשן אשר תאכל האש את
העלה על המזבח ושמו אצל המזבח.
velovash hacohen mido bad umichnesei vad yilbash al besaro veherim es hadashen
asher tochal ha'eish es ha'olah
al hamizbe'ach vesamo etzel hamizbe'ach. So that's
the daily מצוה mitzvah of putting
a bunch of ashes by the side of the מזבח. mizbe'ach. ושמו
אצל המזבח. vesamo etzel hamizbe'ach. Then when it comes to talk about
this bird sacrifice what does it say? It says let me just
find a פסוק. pasuk.
Hold on.
I'm sorry it's earlier.
Yeah so this is about an עולה, olah, ואם מן העוף עלה
קרבנו להשם, ve'im min ha'of olah korbano laHashem, והסיר מראתו בנצתה והשליך
אתה אצל המזבח קדמה אל מקום הדשן. vehesir muraso benotzasa vehishlicho etzel
hamizbe'ach kedma el mekom hadashen. Okay
so both of them say אצל המזבח. etzel hamizbe'ach. So why doesn't
says the גמרא Gemara we didn't need it to say explicitly by
the birds אל מקום הדשן. el mekom hadashen. It could have just
said אצל המזבח etzel hamizbe'ach and if I would have to know
which אצל המזבח etzel hamizbe'ach I would have made a גזירה שוה
gezeira shava by the תרומת הדשן trumas hadashen where it says אצל
המזבח. etzel hamizbe'ach. So this word אל מקום הדשן el mekom hadashen
the place of the ashes is redundant because even without that I
would have made a גזירה שוה. gezeira shava. מאי הדשן? mai hadashen?
Why is it once again tell me that there's this significance of
this place of ashes? דאפילו מזבח הפנימי de'afilu mizbe'ach hapnimi that this
ashes place is a place even for the ashes of the inner
of the inner מזבח. mizbe'ach. It's seen as an extra word here,
and it's to tell me that it's a place of ashes even
for the inner מזבח. Mizbe'ach. מנורה מנלן, Menorah minalan, how do I
know that the ashes of the מנורה Menorah go there? דשן הדשן.
Deshen Hadeshen. The extra ה hei somehow emphasizing this is the place
of ashes, even the ashes for the inner מזבח. Mizbe'ach. So the
גמרא Gemara basically completely ignores the משנה Mishna and the discussion about
the discussion about the discussion about when is there, why is there
no מעילה Me'ila at what stage there's no מעילה Me'ila for the
ashes, which is what I gave you the whole explanation נעשה מצוותו
Na'asa Mitzvaso at an earlier stage, because there's no particular מצוה Mitzvah
of תרומת הדשן. Terumas Hadeshen. That's the way תוספות Tosafos understands, that's
why as soon as it becomes ashes and maybe earlier there's none.
But interestingly, although there's no מצוה Mitzvah of תרומת הדשן, Terumas Hadeshen,
we have now said that the place the ashes go is the
same place as תרומת הדשן. Terumas Hadeshen. And I should point out
that that's conceptually different because by the outer מזבח, Mizbe'ach, when you're
really cleaning it off, the ashes go outside of the בית המקדש.
Beis Ha-Mikdash. When you're doing the symbolic removal of ashes and there
is a מצוה Mitzvah of תרומת הדשן, Terumas Hadeshen, you put it
nearby. And here what the גמרא Gemara is saying is that you
know if there's no מצוה Mitzvah תרומת הדשן, Terumas Hadeshen, which is
why the מעילה Me'ila thing ends earlier, even if there's no מצוה
Mitzvah of תרומת הדשן Terumas Hadeshen when you're really cleaning them off,
the place that you put the ashes of the inner מזבח Mizbe'ach
and of the מנורה, Menorah, the place even when you're just cleaning
it out, not because of a ritual מצוה Mitzvah of תרומת הדשן,
Terumas Hadeshen, goes at the same place. Okay, so that's quite interesting
that that's not even discussed in the משנה, Mishna, and as I
said, it raises questions because it seems to make it like there's
a מצוה Mitzvah תרומת הדשן Terumas Hadeshen by those. Anyway, that is
the גמרא. Gemara. Okay, so that's the ashes. Now the next משנה
Mishna gets on to the issue of the birds, which is more
which gets us back to some earlier discussions. So we had just
said that the birds, there's no מעילה, Me'ila, though we hadn't said
why. So let's take a look. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon אומר תורין
שלא הגיע זמנם מועלין בהם. omer Torin she-lo higia zmanan mo'alin bahem.
One minute, says רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, if you sanctify birds that
are too young, then there is מעילה, Me'ila, because they'll just get
older and they'll be fit to bring a קרבן. Korban. Right? So
why should there not be מעילה? Me'ila? At least they'll be fit
to bring a קרבן, Korban, you know, just wait. בני יונה שעבר
זמנם, Bnei Yona she-avar zmanan, however, when it's בני יונה Bnei Yona
that are too old, then I agree with you, לא נהנין ולא
מועלין בהם, lo nehenin ve-lo mo'alin bahem, there there's no מעילה Me'ila
because then they can't be used at all. So now the first
thing I should point out is everybody agrees when the birds are
too old. That's more, you know, as clear, then they can't be
used. But why is it different than a normal animal קרבן Korban
with a מום? Mum? So I said this yesterday, it's different because
in those, this you cannot you can't redeem, there's no פדיון Pidyon
by עופות. Ofos. Even if it's missing a limb, it's never possible
to do פדיון Pidyon by birds, and therefore it's something which like
the גמרא Gemara said by חטאת העוף, Chatas Ha-Of, הולך לאיבוד. holech
le-ibud. The קדושה Kedusha cannot go anywhere right now. Okay? There's nothing
that can be done, it's הולך לאיבוד, holech le-ibud, so therefore everybody
agrees that there's no מעילה. Me'ila. But question is, as רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon rightly says, it shouldn't apply to birds that are too
young, right? And why would those be no מעילה? Me'ila? Just wait.
So let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. בשלמא Bishlama רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon כדיקתני טעמא. kide-katani ta'ama. רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, we
understand why you know what his position is, as it we even
say explicitly in a ברייתא, Braita, שהיה רבי שמעון אומר, she-haya Rabbi
Shimon omer, כל הראוי לאחר זמן, kol ha-ra'uy le-achar zman, I'm sorry,
not ברייתא, Braita, in the משנה, Mishna, שכל הראוי לאחר זמן והקדישו
בתוך זמנו הרי הוא בלא תעשה ואין בו כרת. she-kol ha-ra'uy le-achar
zman vehikdisho betoch zmano harei hu belo sa'aseh ve-ein bo kares. Now
this is an analogy, but remember way back in חולין, Chullin, the
discussion of אותו ואת בנו, oso ve-es beno, slaughtering a child and
a mother animal on the same day. What would be if those
animals were קדשים? Kodshim? So משנה Mishna says it's נוהג בקדשים. noheg
be-kodshim. Okay, so let's say you
slaughtered the mother and then you went ahead and and you slaughtered
the child on the same day. But just one second, let me
hold on, and you slaughtered it, let me just one second, right,
and you slaughtered it outside the בית המקדש. Beis Ha-Mikdash. Do people
remember this משנה Mishna in חולין? Chullin? Right, it had you slaughtering
קרבנות Korbanos in the בית המקדש, Beis Ha-Mikdash, out of the בית
המקדש, Beis Ha-Mikdash, אותו ואת בנו oso ve-es beno anyway, it was
a whole interesting set of cases. So that's what you did. You
took this child sheep, the mother was slaughtered earlier today. You sanctified
the child sheep and you slaughtered it outside the בית המקדש. Beis
Ha-Mikdash. Are you חייב? chayav? You're חייב chayav for אותו ואת בנו.
oso ve-es beno. Are you חייב chayav for שחוטי חוץ? shechutei chutz?
Why shouldn't you be חייב chayav for שחוטי חוץ? shechutei chutz? Because
שחוטי חוץ shechutei chutz is only something ראוי ra'uy to be brought
as a קרבן. Korban. This cannot be brought as a קרבן Korban
today because it's of the איסור issur of אותו ואת בנו. oso
ve-es beno. So what does רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon say? So let's
read it again. He says כל הראוי לאחר זמן והקדישו בתוך זמנו,
kol ha-ra'uy le-achar zman vehikdisho betoch zmano, anything that will be fit
later and you sanctified it now בתוך זמנו, betoch zmano, meaning today
it can't be brought as a קרבן Korban because its mother was
slaughtered, and you go ahead and you slaughter it outside the בית
המקדש, Beis Ha-Mikdash, הרי הוא בלא תעשה, harei hu belo sa'aseh, you
transgress the לאו lav of slaughtering a קרבן Korban out of the
בית המקדש, Beis Ha-Mikdash, ואין בו כרת, ve-ein bo kares, there's no
כרת. kares. So he says an interesting middle position. If this is
will be fit later, it's in a middle state where because later
it will be fit, it's enough to transgress the prohibition. not bringing
it of שחיטה shechting it outside the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. But
because it's not fit now, you're not going to get כרת. kares.
What interests us is not the exemption of כרת, kares, but the
fact that he says you at least did transgress. You transgressed שחיטה
shechting outside, even though right now it couldn't be brought at all.
Why? Because it will be able to be brought later. So what
the גמרא Gemara is saying is we see that רבי שמעון Rebbi
Shimon says something that later will be fit gives it significance now
even before it's ready. So we understand why he would say his
position about the birds. Okay, fine, that that is מעילה. me'ilah. אלא
רבנן, Ella rabanan, but the rabbis, even if they disagree implicitly with
רבי שמעון'ס Rebbi Shimon's idea about שחוטי חוץ, shechutei chutz, shechting this
thing that's not yet ready outside the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, משמע
מיני מחוסר זמן. mashma minei mechusar zman. And this is the question
Charlie asked. So Charlie, you anticipated the גמרא. Gemara. What if you
sanctified an animal that was less than eight days old? Forget שחוטי
חוץ shechutei chutz that רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon discussed. Whatever, but the
point is, would there be מעילה me'ilah if you sanctified an animal
less than eight days old? Of course, right? So and nobody ever
said not. Of course it would be. So the birds should be
the exact same story. It'll be ready in a week, a year,
whatever it'll be, it'll be a little while and then it'll be
fit for a קרבן. korban. Why should it be different than sanctifying
an animal that is less than eight days old? So let's see
what the גמרא Gemara says. אמרי, Amri, they say no. מחוסר זמן
mechusar zman מידי דהוי אבעל מום. midi dehavai aba'al mum.
מחוסר זמן mechusar zman you get מעילה me'ilah because the same way
you would have מעילה me'ilah if the sheep, let's say, wasn't three
days old, but if the sheep had a blemish. Why is there
מעילה me'ilah there? דבר פדיון הוא. d'var pidyon hu. It is something
that could be redeemed. And the fact that it could be redeemed
means that even though it can't be brought right now, the קדושה
kedusha can be seen as purposeful, has something that could go somewhere,
even if it couldn't be used in this thing right now. אבל
הני עופות, aval hani ofos, these birds, כיון דאין מום פוסל בעוף,
keivan d'ein mum posel b'of, since there's no concept of a blemish
by birds—now the תוספות Tosafos says it's not really about there being
no concept of a blemish. There is a concept of מחוסר אבר,
mechusar eiver, missing a limb. Okay, but תוספות Tosafos says that's not
really what it means. What it really means is nothing wrong with
birds will ever allow you to redeem them. Okay, so therefore אין
לעופות פדיון, ein l'ofos pidyon, they can't be redeemed. So I know
this גמרא Gemara makes it sound like they can't be redeemed because
there's no הלכה halacha of מום, mum, but תוספות Tosafos says obviously
that's לאו דוקא. lav davka. And therefore because they can't be redeemed,
if they can't be used as a קרבן korban right
now, there is no מעילה me'ilah by them. Now again, I have
to say that I don't really conceptually understand this. Meaning, I understand
saying that if it's not able to ever be brought, like it's
too old, then you could say, okay. But if it's a type
of קרבן korban that you could envision could get a מום mum
and you could transfer the קדושה, kedusha, the קדושה kedusha could still
have a purpose and could still eventually, it could go somewhere, then
there's מעילה. me'ilah. If it's a type of a קרבן korban like
a חטאת המתה chatas hamaisa or a bird that's too old that
you're just going to have to let die, then the קדושה kedusha
isn't going anywhere, there's no מעילה. me'ilah. So there's where the idea
of the option of פדיון pidyon makes a difference. But when it's
too young, okay, it's true, if this bird got stuck as it
were and got into a place where you couldn't use it, the
קדושה kedusha wouldn't be going anywhere. But right now, the קדושה kedusha
is going somewhere. You wait a week, you'll wait a month, and
then you'll be able to bring this bird as a קרבן. korban.
So it's not so clear to me why this idea that it's
fit for פדיון pidyon or not, if there were a problem, should
affect whether you see it right now as whether the קדושה kedusha
is significant enough to have מעילה. me'ilah. Unless you sort of just
think very abstractly and you say, right now it can't be brought.
Okay, well, if you're talking about not birds but animals, the fact
that something can't be brought is never an impediment to מעילה me'ilah
because there's always possibilities of פדיון. pidyon. Not that that's relevant right
here, here it's just about waiting some days, but the concept that
it can't be brought is not sort of fundamentally going to get
the קדושה kedusha stuck. Here, because it can't be brought right now,
there are cases when it can't be brought that's going to get
the קדושה kedusha stuck. So even though that's not the case right
now, because the קדושה kedusha isn't stuck, wait a few days, somehow
that's enough to problematize the
קדושה.
kedusha. But anyway, that's the
גמרא's Gemara answer.
רבי שמעון's Rebbi Shimon position certainly is
more attractive. Alright, now
the
גמרא Gemara goes on. אמר עולא אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Ulla amar
Rabbi Yochanan, moving on. קדשים שמתו יצאו מידי מעילה דבר תורה. Kodashim
shemeisu yatzu mi'yedei me'ilah d'var Torah.
Now this is, this is interesting because again, I'm trying to sort
of bring together the relevant stuff we've been learning. On the one
hand, if something is just פסול, pasul, the bird case excluded, there
still is, you know, there still is מעילה. me'ila. It was קדושה,
kedusha, it's not going to become הותר, hutar, and there still is
מעילה. me'ila. The פסול pasul doesn't get it out of the category.
What does get it out of the category is if it's הולך
לאיבוד holech l'ibud like a חטאת המתה chatas hamesa or the two
old birds. Now we're talking about what happens if it actually, there
was no פסול pasul with it, but at the other end, it
died. It died before you could bring it as a קרבן. korban.
Now remember if you שחטed shacht it and it's פסול pasul and
you're going to have to now, you can't use the dead carcass,
what are you going to do, that was the first משנה, Mishna,
you're going to burn it. Okay, you're going to burn it like
you have a ritual burning of פסולי מוקדשים. psulei mukdashim. There, there
is מעילה. me'ila. But if it died, that's considered to take it
completely out of the category. One way of understanding the difference between
died and שחטing shacht it when it's פסול pasul is שחטing shacht
when it's פסול pasul there's still a מצוה mitzva of שריפה shreifa
because מצות שריפה mitzvas shreifa of פסולי מוקדשים psulei mukdashim in the
בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. So it still is in the world of
קדושה. kedusha. You could also say נעשית מצותו. na'asis mitzvaso. But if
it died, then there's no מצוה mitzva of what to do with
it. It's totally, you know, now not usable. So that's sort of
the other end of הולך לאיבוד. holech l'ibud. So there's some פסולים
psulim which don't, most פסולים psulim don't remove the קדושה kedusha and
even after the animal is dead doesn't remove the קדושה kedusha because
there's a מצות שריפה. mitzvas shreifa. But at the one end if
it's פסול psul so much that it's הולך לאיבוד, holech l'ibud, then
that's, that's no מעילה. me'ila. And at the other end if it
actually was איבוד, ibud, if it died in a way that was
not a, was not a פסול בקודש, psul bakodesh, but it just
dropped dead and there's no מצות שריפה mitzvas shreifa anymore, then that
also is no מעילה. me'ila. Yes.
What about a case where it was שחטed shacht and the שחיטה
shchita was not done correctly?
That was the first משנה. Mishna. That's what I was saying. Yeah.
Oh you mean שחיטה פסולה shchita psula like a טרפה treifa like
a...
No I mean whoever שחטed shacht it screwed up and did...
right, right, right, so the physical מעשה שחיטה. ma'aseh shchita. Right. So
that would be a קדשים שמתו kodshim shemeisu type of case. That
wouldn't be a הקדש פסול. hekdesh pasul. That would just be, that
would basically be, you know, a קדשים שמתו kodshim shemeisu type of
scenario. So that's the thing. If it basically is considered to have
died and not in a way that gives it a status of
פסולי מוקדשים psulei mukdashim in a way there's no מצוה mitzva to
burn it, then there's not going to be, then there's not going
to be מעילה. me'ila. So אמר ליה רב יוחנן קדשים שמתו יצאו
מידי מעילה. Amar lei Rav Yochanan Kodshim shemeisu yatz'u miday me'ila. They
got out of their מעילה me'ila category. דאורייתא. D'oraisa. יתבי וקאמרי להא
שמעתא. Yasvei v'ka'amrei l'ha shma'sa. So רב עולא Rav Ulla was saying
over and telling over the teaching in the name of רב יוחנן.
Rav Yochanan. אמר ליה רב חסדא. Amar lei Rav Chisda. So רב
חסדא Rav Chisda said back to him. מאן שמע לך ולרב יוחנן
רבך. Man shama lach ul'Rav Yochanan rabach. Who's going to listen to
you and רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan your rebbe that says such a
crazy thing that there's no מעילה. me'ila. Why? והרי קדושה שבהן היכן
הלכה. V'harei kedusha shebahen heichan halcha. Where did the קדושה kedusha go
to? How can you mean there's no מעילה? me'ila? It was קדוש.
kadosh. Now get this. It's pretty funny. We talked a minute ago
about different scenarios of קדושה kedusha that there's no מעילה me'ila for.
But apparently what he's saying is, okay, if the קדושה kedusha started
off as problematic, right? It was קדשים שמתו kodshim shemeisu or some
type of a bird where it's also going to have to potentially
הולך לאיבוד. holech l'ibud. Fine, the קדושה kedusha never made it fit
for, for מעילה. me'ila. But this was a קדושה kedusha that was
totally fine, I was about to bring it as a קרבן korban
and it dropped dead on me. How does that make the קדושה
kedusha go away just because it dropped dead? It still has קדושה.
kedusha. אמר ליה. Amar lei. So he said back to him. ותיפוק
לי ממתניתין. V'sifok li m'matnisin. How about our משנה? Mishna? תורין שלא
הגיע זמנם ובני יונה שעבר זמנם לא נהנין ולא מועלין. Torin shelo
higia zmanam uvnei yona she'avar zmanam lo nehenin v'lo moalin. So this
case about the birds, right? You, so there's no מעילה. me'ila. הכא
נמי נימא קדושה שבהן היכן הלכה. Hacha nami neima kedusha shebahen heichan
halcha. Where did the קדושה kedusha go to? Now why is that
a question? There as we said the קדושה kedusha never started as
being ראוי. ra'ui. Okay, but not really because what תוספות Tosafos says,
we've been talking about you're מקדיש makdish it too young and it,
why can't you just wait for it to get older? But תוספות
Tosafos says what about the scenario that not that you were מקדיש
makdish it too old, but you were מקדיש makdish the birds at
the right age and then they got too old? You see that
scenario? So when you originally were מקדיש makdish it, it was good.
Now they got too old because the משנה Mishna just says, right,
it says תורין שלא הגיע זמנם. torin shelo higia zmanam. It didn't
say when you were מקדיש makdish it. It just says now they're
too old. So that's exactly the case. The קדושה kedusha started good,
now it became unusable and it says there's no מעילה. me'ila. תוספות
Tosafos says you could have also asked from the first משנה Mishna
of the פרק perek about a חטאת המתה. chatas hamesa. חטאת המתה
Chatas hamesa doesn't have to be a case where you initially sanctified
it in a bad way. It could be you sanctified it and
then you brought another קרבן korban
and
then
this one becomes נתכפרו בעליה באחרת niskafru
ba'aleha b'acheres becomes a חטאת המתה. chatas hamesa. So he's basically like
what are you talking about? Our פרק perek is full of cases
that the קדושה kedusha might have started good, became
bad, and we say
there's no מעילה. me'ila. So what are
you bothering me? So אמר ליה. Amar lei. So he said back
to him. מודינא לך. Modina lach. Okay, I can see the point.
I admit דאיכא מעילה מדרבנן. d'ika me'ila m'derabbanan. But at least what
I... this is the way תוספות Tosafos read it, the language is
a little funny, but basically I admit the point, I concede, but
I still say you know that there should be, that there should
be דרבנן מעילה. derabbanan me'ila. It's not that there should be no
מעילה. me'ila. He said back to him, מודים לך, Modim lach, okay,
I can see the point. I admit the איכא מעילה מדרבנן. ika
me'ila miderabbanan. But at least what I—this is the way תוספות Tosfos
read it, the language is a little funny—but basically, I admit the
point, I concede, but I still say, you know, that there should
be—there should be דרבנן מעילה. derabbanan me'ila. It's not that there should
be no מעילה. me'ila. Of course, עולא Ulla said יצא מידי מעילה
דאורייתא, yatza midei me'ila d'oraisa, so it's a question if עולא Ulla
really would deny that. But anyway, basically, he conceded the point. Fine,
it starts with the קדושה, kedusha, but if it gets to a
stage where either it's הולך לאיבוד, holech l'ibud, okay, which is now
חטאת המתה chatas hamesa or two old bird, it started good but
it's הולך לאיבוד holech l'ibud or it actually is איבוד, ibud, it
died, okay, and not in a way that's פסולו בקודש. psulo bakodesh.
So in those types of cases there's no מעילה, me'ila. but at
least there's דרבנן מעילה.
derabbanan me'ila Now that's not so
clear, because when our משנה Mishnah said לא נהנין ולא מועלין lo
nehenin v'lo moalin by the birds and the חטאת המתה, chatas hamesa,
לא נהנין lo nehenin is not the same as רבנן מעילה. rabbanan
me'ila. The primary difference is, besides that רבנן מעילה rabbanan me'ila sounds
more חמור, chamur, but the primary difference is do you pay back
or not, right? By רבנן מעילה rabbanan me'ila you pay back, by
לא נהנין lo nehenin it's just an איסור הנאה issur hana'ah benefit.
So what he is doing is, he wants to emphasize, if it
starts with good קדושה kedusha it should retain קדושה, kedusha, it should
retain it, fine, I can see the point, not דאורייתא, d'oraisa, but
at least דרבנן. derabbanan And basically he wants to read in all
of the cases we've been dealing with that there's רבנן מעילה. rabbanan
me'ila. Okay, so let's take a look. What's איבוד? ibud? What is
איבוד? ibud? איבוד ibud to waste, to destroy, to be destroyed. Okay,
וקשיא ליה, v'kashya leh, so what was bothering me? מי איכא מידי
דמעיקרא לא אית ביה מעילה ולבסוף אית ביה מעילה? mi ika midi
d'meikara lo is bei me'ila u'lesof is bei me'ila? Here's is there
something that originally
there's no מעילה me'ila, and at
the end there is מעילה? me'ila Now what is that case? We've
had cases where it started perhaps with מעילה, me'ila? you were מקדיש
makdish the birds too young and so on, where and then they
got old, you were מקדיש makdish the קרבן korban and it became
a חטאת המתה, chatas hamesa, where's the case where it started with
no מעילה me'ila, and it got מעילה? me'ila So that case is
what? We just had that. Which case? The דם. dam. So the
גמרא's Gemara going to bring that in, but which case is bothering
him? So hold on one second, let me just check תוספות. Tosfos.
תוספות Tosfos say the אימורין imurin of קדשים קלים. kodshim kalim. Ah,
that's true too. So he does, so that's good that you thought
about קדשים קלים kodshim kalim because that's what תוספות Tosfos reads into
this. For some, but he's not reading the אימורין imurin of קדשים
קלים kodshim kalim which is a real דאורייתא d'oraisa case where the
status changes, he's talking here where something in a sense gets worse,
gets further away from being קדוש kadosh and now there's מעילה. me'ila?
And where would he have that? Because עולא Ulla said קדשים שמתו,
kodshim shemesu, here's the point, עולא Ulla said קדשים שמתו יצאו מידי
מעילה דאורייתא. kodshim shemesu yatza midei me'ila d'oraisa. So he understands what
you mean is דאורייתא d'oraisa no מעילה, דרבנן me'ila derabbanan. there is
מעילה. me'ila. But if קדשים שמתו kodshim shemesu includes קדשים קלים, kodshim
kalim, so קדשים קלים kodshim kalim when they're alive there's no מעילה,
me'ila, right? That's קדשים קלים kodshim kalim when they're alive. Now they
died, now you're going to tell me there's דרבנן derabbanan. מעילה me'ila.
afterwards? How does it become worse even though the worse is only
a דרבנן derabbanan stage? Okay, so that's what he's saying bothers me.
I concede that when it's died or when it became unusable קדושה
kedusha as it were, הולך לאיבוד, holech l'ibud, that there's no מעילה
דאורייתא. me'ila d'oraisa. But you're implicitly saying, because you say דאורייתא, d'oraisa,
that there is מעילה דרבנן. me'ila derabbanan? And what's bothering me is
how would you really say something starts without מעילה me'ila, and then
has מעילה דרבנן? me'ila derabbanan? So implicitly the קדשים קלים kodshim kalim
case, if they died, would you really say that now they have
מעילה דרבנן? me'ila derabbanan. So that's the question he's struck with. What?
That's stricter. Right, and they're getting, it's not like the אימורי קדשים
קלים imurei kodshim kalim which are getting closer to the מזבח, mizbe'ach,
here it's dying, it's getting further away as it were and now
it's stricter because there's מעילה דרבנן. me'ila derabbanan. So that's his question.
So the גמרא Gemara says לא lo and now it says what
you said, what about the blood? ואיכא דם? v'ika dam? And that
also is getting further away from the מזבח mizbe'ach because נעשית מצותו
na'asis mitzvaso and then it becomes still מעילה דרבנן. Me'ilah d'Rabbanan. דמעיקרא
לית ביה מעילה ולבסוף אית ביה מעילה, d'meikara leis bei me'ila u'lesof
is bei me'ila, originally there's no מעילה me'ila and at the end
there is מעילה. me'ila דתנן, d'isnan, דם בתחילה אין מועלין בו, dam
batchila ein moalin bo, there's no מעילה me'ila. originally. Once it's done
and it gets further away, יצא לנחל קדרון, yatza l'nachal kidron, physically
further away, it goes out to the wadi and it's done, מועלין
בו, moalin bo, there is מעילה, me'ila at least דרבנן. derabbanan So
you can have stuff that after the fact we apply more דרבנן's,
derabbanan. maybe there's more of a reason to be concerned people will
sin once it's now dead and once it's now washed away blood
and so on. So he says, what? That it was already used.
What? That's true. Anyway, התם נמי איכא מעילה מעיקרא, hasam nami ika
me'ila meikara, the גמרא Gemara says no, התם נמי איכא מעילה מעיקרא,
hasam nami ika me'ila meikara, that doesn't bother me so much because
there's a way you could have מעילה me'ila, by blood even earlier.
How could you have מעילה me'ila by blood earlier?
דאמר רב המקיז דם לבהמת קדשים אסור בהנאה ומועלין בו. d'amar rav
hamequiz dam l'behemas kodshim assur bahana'ah u'moalin bo. That if you actually
let blood for an animal that was a קרבן korban because it
was going to, you know, it had blood clotting or whatever, they
would often let blood when there was, you know, when they thought
that that was a way of therapeutic. So you had this animal
you were afraid it was going to die, you let blood. That
blood that comes out of it is you're actually going to be
an איסור מעילה. issur me'ila. Now why is that different than the
דם dam that you use for the whole, you know, מצוה mitzvah
to go on the מזבח? mizbe'ach? So if you remember, the whole
reason that blood was excluded was based on פסוקים *psukim* that said,
I've given it to you on the מזבח mizbe'ach *mizbe'ach* לכפר *lechaper*,
לכפר ולא למעילה *lechaper velo leme'ilah*. I've given it to you לכם
*lachem* and therefore you shouldn't have מעילה me'ila *me'ilah*. So all of
that only applied to blood that was being used for כפרה *kaparah*.
If you actually have blood that came from an animal that's a
קרבן Korban *korban* that was not being used for כפרה *kaparah*, bloodletting,
it got a wound and it was dripping blood, that's a part
of the animal. So therefore the same way there's מעילה me'ilah *me'ilah*
on the animal, there's מעילה me'ilah *me'ilah* on the blood. Okay, so
it's quite ironic. It was ironic enough that there's no מעילה me'ilah
*me'ilah* by the blood, now we're seeing that blood actually is מעילה
me'ilah *me'ilah* except for the blood that's being used on the מזבח
mizbe'ach? *mizbe'ach* and the blood that's being used for כפרה *kaparah*. So
anyway, what's his basic point? His point is, so the fact that
you can apply rabbinic מעילה me'ilah *me'ilah* to the blood doesn't bother
me, says it's not a concept that's inappropriate to blood, even though
we're talking about different bloods where it was used. But I don't
understand how you can apply מעילה me'ilah. *me'ilah* to something that never
דרבנן derabbanan *derabbanan* that never had מעילה me'ilah. *me'ilah* like קדשים kodshim
קלים *kodshim kalim* that died. There would never be a concept of
מעילה me'ilah, *me'ilah* on the meat of קדשים קלים *kodshim kalim* that
would become completely a foreign concept, and here you're going to tell
me once things die we're going to have a rabbinic מעילה me'ilah
*me'ilah*. So that's left as a question. But the upshot is, the
upshot is, is that again to try to make you sort of
see the scope of this, if things become הולך לאיבוד *holech le'ibud*
basically unusable, have to let die like the חטאת chatas. *chatat* or
the bird even when alive, then that's going to be out of
מעילה me'ilah *me'ilah*. If it's a פסול pasul *pasul* like פסול בקודש
*pasul bakodesh* and there's a מצוה mitzvah שריפה *mitzvah sreifah* even though
it's פסול *pasul* can't be used, there still is מעילה Me'ilah, *me'ilah*.
And at the back end or the whatever, if it dies, even
if it was a good קדושה kedusha *kedushah*, once it's dead and
it wasn't פסולה בקודש *pasula bakodesh*, wasn't שחט *shechted* with a פסול
*pasul*, but it actually died, dropped dead, then also no מעילה Me'ilah,
*me'ilah*. The קדושה kedusha *kedushah* is basically seen as having no longer
any, it's not going anywhere, it's been wasted and so on. And
then the only thing being introduced here is that maybe there would
still be rabbinic מעילה Me'ilah. *me'ilah*, not דאורייתא *de'Oraita* מעילה Me'ilah *me'ilah*
but rabbinic מעילה Me'ilah *me'ilah*. Rifka, yeah?
Yeah, I'm thinking about that phrase, where did the קדושה kedusha *kedushah*
go? קדושה kedusha להיכן הלכה halacha? *kedushah l'heichan halchah*? Are they seeing
קדושה kedusha *kedushah* like טומאה *tum'ah* is almost something tangible and you
have to atone for it, you have to do something to get
rid of it? Is קדושה kedusha *kedushah* seen that way?
That's an interesting question. I mean it's the same question about how
they
see,
right, right, it's got to go somewhere, it dissipates, right.
I think that's an interesting point because that's a good point to
ask, meaning you could see קדושה kedusha *kedushah* as a status.
But you're saying this
terminology, if you said how did it stop becoming קדוש kadosh, *kadosh*
then fine, I'm seeing it as a status. But saying where did
it go, I'm seeing it as some type of a thing that
inhabits. And you are right as well that by טומאה *tum'ah* that's
also the question. Do you view it as some type of a
metaphysical force that spreads and that transfers? And I think you're right
like, that is the probably the way, the easiest way to imagine
conceptually how these are being dealt with.
Yeah, I think that's a good point. I'm not sure
whether there's הלכה halachah *halachic* implications to framing it that
way, but we often talk about like do you instill קדושה kedushah
*kedushah* into the object or when you redeem it you transfer the
קדושה kedusha *kedushah* from the object to the money. So I think
you're right that we sort of conceptualize it as if it's this
ethereal thing that somehow is non-physical thing that is inhabiting the animal,
inhabiting the money, it's transferring from one to the other.
And it doesn't just disappear and dissipate, it goes. You have to
account for it.
Right, well of course if you bury the animal then it goes
into the ground with the animal, it doesn't
need another host afterwards.
But I think that's a good point, I think that's a good
point that yeah, that is implicit in the phrasing. Okay, good. So
anyway, we had the תיקו *teiku* or something or
was that me who was just...
Yeah, I don't know, he's just, because it wasn't such a big
question, he's just saying I don't like the idea that you're giving
it a דרבנן d'Rabbanan *derabbanan* status afterwards if it didn't have it
before. And you say well we have a precedent, I don't think
that that's a good answer because I think דם *dam* is different.
Okay, you don't like it.
He didn't have an evidence against it, he just said how could
that be? And he says oh yeah there's another case but I
don't think that דם *dam* I don't feel that that's a good
example. So okay, if you could say fine you don't feel it's
a good example, I feel it's a good example. Alright, moving on.
So okay, that's the גופא *gufa*. Now we're going to get to
this interesting question about the parts of the animal to which the
מעילה Me'ilah *me'ilah* applies. אמר רב הונא אמר רב המקיז דם בבהמת
קדשים אסור בהנאה assur behana'ah. *Amar Rav Huna amar Rav hamakis dam
b'vehemat kodshim assur b'hana'ah*. Okay, that's what we just said, if you
actually let blood, that blood is אסור בהנאה *assur b'hana'ah*, not only
אסור בהנאה *assur b'hana'ah*, מועלין בו *mo'alin bo*. It's really considered as
if it were part of the animal and if there's מעילה Me'ilah
*me'ilah* to the animal there's מעילה me'ilah, *me'ilah* to this blood as
long as it's not the blood being used on the
מזבח mizbe'ach *mizbe'ach*. מתיב רב המנונא *Masiv Rav Hamnuna*, so רב המנונא
*Rav Hamnuna* asks, כל המוקדשים וביצי תורין torin *kol hamo'ukdashim u'veitzei torin*,
this is the משנה Mishnah. *mishnah* that we're about to read. If
you have the ממש the next משנה. mishna If you have milk
from a female
קרבן korban or eggs from the pigeons or the turtledoves, לא נהנין
ולא מועלין. lo nehenin velo mo'alin. It specifically says תורין because those
are the ones that they're the adults, so they're laying the eggs.
לא נהנין ולא מועלין. lo nehenin velo mo'alin. There's not, you can't
derive הנאה, hana'ah, but there's no מעילה me'ilah because it's not the
קרבן korban, itself. It's a product of the קרבן, korban it's not
the קרבן korban. itself. So therefore, there's no מעילה me'ilah, on them,
okay? Alright. So how is blood any different? אמר ליה: Amar lei:
כי קאמינא לגבי דם, ki kamina legabei dam, I'm only talking about
blood, דלא מתקיים בלא דם, delo miskayem belo dam, an animal can't
live without blood. Blood is the life force, and therefore the blood
of an animal is seen like the meat of the animal, and
therefore it's seen like the animal itself, it's not just seen as
a product of the animal. אבל חלב, Aval chalav, but milk, דקא
מקיים בלא חלב, deka mikayem belo chalav, an animal can live without
its own producing milk, right? לא, Lo, I wouldn't say that. These
things are just products of the animal, they're not actually part, intrinsic
parts of the animal, and therefore there's no מעילה me'ilah? by them.
Yes.
The milk from the
consecrated בהמה behemah would have to be from a חטאת. chatas Right.
Or a שלמים. shlamim. Well, שלמים, shlamim, though there's no מעילה me'ilah.
by a שלמים shlamim until the... right. Yes.
How do you distinguish that from, let's say, from like the wool
of a sheep?
Well, isn't it the... I mean, the same point, that an animal,
you mean because it can't live because it'll be like freeze to
death?
No, no, no. It should be like the eggs.
Oh, I think it is.
And there's no מעילה me'ilah.
on the wool? But there was מעילה.
me'ilah, Well,
I guess the milk and the eggs naturally separate from the animal.
Right.
Whereas the wool, you have
to shear the sheep.
Right. Milk could be naturally... You have to milk sheep? Well.
But it's sort of biologically produced so that it will... so that
it will separate. The biology is that. That's a good point.
Actually the wool comes off... I'm sorry? In a season the wool
comes off naturally.
But yeah,
you're probably right though, since the only thing being excluded is the
eggs and the milk, the implication is that the wool would be...
Yeah, actually now that I'm remembering, I think it's pretty מפורש. meforash.
I'll have to double-check that.
But there was a whole thing written about wool.
What? About the... well, just that you can't use it doesn't prove
that there's מעילה. me'ilah. That's the question, if there is... Alright, I'll
have to check on that. But
yeah, there is a difference as well that these things are made
to separate from the body. Okay, so let's see where the גמרא
Gemara goes with this.
מתיב רב משרשיא: Masiv Rav Mesharshaya: הזבל והפרש שבחצר, ha-zevel veha-peresh shebe-chatzer,
לא נהנין ולא מועלין בהן, lo nehenin velo mo'alin bahen, ויפלו דמיהן
ללשכה. veyippelu demeihen lallishkah. So if you actually have in a field
where there were קדשים animals,
dung, or פירש peresh is also types of like waste products that
came from the animal, not exactly sure how it would be different
than dung, then you cannot derive benefit, but there's no מעילה, me'ilah.
ויפלו דמיהן ללשכה, veyippelu demeihen lallishkah, and therefore you use the money
for Temple proceeds. אמאי? Amai? הכא נמי לא מקיים בלא פירש? hacha
nami lo mikayem belo peresh? An animal can't exist without some of
its undigested food. פירש Peresh is different, like dung is the real
dung and פירש peresh is like the undigested food in its stomach.
I'm not sure how that undigested food got out into the field,
but okay. Anyway, it says an animal can't exist without that. It
assumes, I don't know if this is true, it assumes somehow that
an animal always needs to have some undigested food in its stomach.
Charlie?
Well, if it
starves to death...
Yeah, right. No, but for... but if it's not starving
to death, it has to have it at every minute of its...
Alright, anyway, so that's anyway, that's what the גמרא Gemara says. אמרי,
Amrei, מאי איריא, mai irya, הדין פירש דמעלמא קאתי לה. hadein peresh
de-me'alma ka'asi lah. When if food in its stomach, undigested food, it's
still coming from the
outside, אזיל האי ואתי אחרינא. azil hai ve-asi achrina. So even if
it always needs some in its system, but it's always being processed
through its system, there's no... right, and therefore anything is never considered
part of the
animal, לאפוקי דם דמגופיה הוא, la'appokei dam di-gufeih hu, as opposed to
blood. Now of course the body does produce blood, but it's the
body itself producing blood, and as the מפרש mefaresh says also, we're
born with blood in our system. So therefore blood is always seen
as something that is intrinsic and therefore even when it comes out,
it's a part of the animal and there is מעילה me'ilah, on
it. So you made a face, you're not buying the
answer? You really think that food in your system is considered part
of you?
No, on the contrary, I think... I don't even really understand the
question.
Right, that's what he said, מאי איריא, mai irya, what type of
question was that? Okay.
Alright.
So now the גמרא Gemara goes on, הכא קתני לא נהנין ולא
מועלין ודמיהן ללשכה. hacha katani lo nehenin velo mo'alin u-demeihen lallishkah. That
that we taught that this dung that comes from animals, you can't
derive benefit but there's no... it's not מעילה me'ilah and the money
goes... if the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash will sell it to farmers
and the money will go to the Temple Treasury. מסייע ליה לרבי
אלעזר. Mesayyei lei le-Rabbi Elazar. It supports Rabbi Elazar. דאמר רבי אלעזר:
De-amar Rabbi Elazar: כל מקום שאמרו חכמים קודש ואינו קודש. kol makom
she-ameru chachamim kodesh ve-eino kodesh. Whenever the rabbis said it's quasi-קדוש, which
they say what is explained to mean all these cases of לא
נהנין ולא מועלין, lo nehenin velo mo'alin, that there's an איסור issur
of הנאה hana'ah but not so much that there's a מעילה, me'ilah
all those cases דמיהן יפלו ללשכה, dameihen yiplu l'lishka, the proceeds should
go to the temple treasury. Now, what does this mean?
The מפרש mefareish here says what it means is is that if
you not only does it mean that they that they should sell
it, the temple treasury, you know, they should sell it and take
the proceeds, but it means is that if you even impermissibly derived
benefit from it, that then you give back the money, what you
derived, and that money goes to the temple treasury. That's the consequence
of לא נהנין. lo nehenin. There's no מעילה דאורייתא, Me'ilah d'Oraisa, you
can't derive benefit, if you do then you pay back and the
money goes to the temple treasury. תוספות Tosafos strongly objects to this
read because it says that makes it מעילה דרבנן. Me'ilah d'Rabbanan, The
basic difference between a דרבנן of לא נהנין, lo nehenin, which is
an איסור הנאה, issur hana'ah, and a מעילה דרבנן, Me'ilah d'Rabbanan is
that מעילה דרבנן Me'ilah d'Rabbanan. you have to pay back whatever you
benefited. So תוספות Tosafos refuses that here because the normally the phrase
לא נהנין lo nehenin means no מעילה, me'ilah, even no מעילה דרבנן.
Me'ilah d'Rabbanan, He says all it means is is that that this
is what the this is advice or you know to the temple.
If you have these various objects where there's no איסור מעילה issur
Me'ilah but there's also an איסור הנאה, issur hana'ah, what you guys
should do is you should don't let them go to waste, sell
them and use the proceeds to go to the temple treasury. So
תוספות Tosafos reads that all this is saying is not a consequence
of incorrectly benefiting from it. דמיהן יפלו ללשכה dameihen yiplu l'lishka is
just saying that this is what the temple should be doing with
this stuff to use it. But if you do use it, you've
been over on like an איסור הנאה, issur hana'ah, like being getting
הנאה hana'ah from חמץ chametz on פסח, Pesach, that there's no payment
to be done. That's conceptually the difference. Meaning it's not only the
question of paying, it's the conceptual issue, right? I also can't get
הנאה hana'ah from חמץ chametz on פסח. Pesach. If I do, I
was over on an איסור הנאה. issur hana'ah. There's no concept of
taking something away and having to pay back. You follow? No, because
it's not like חייב כרת chayav kares or whatever for הנאה hana'ah
as opposed to whatever. But so that's an איסור הנאה issur hana'ah
as opposed... and that's what we normally think לא נהנין. lo nehenin.
מעילה דרבנן, Me'ilah d'Rabbanan. which is much more narrow cases, is like
an idea of taking it away. And therefore if I do I
have to give back what I've taken, or if I got הנאה
hana'ah I have to pay the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash for the
הנאה hana'ah that I received. That's the conceptual difference. Okay, so now
let's continue. חלבן וביציהן לא נהנין ולא מועלין, chalvan ubeitzaihen lo nehenin
velo mo'alin, this is what we just quoted. Milk and eggs is
לא נהנין ולא מועלין. lo nehenin velo mo'alin. You don't get הנאה
hana'ah and but there's no
מעילה. ובמה דברים אמורים, uvemeh devarim amurim, when is that true? בקדשי
מזבח, b'kodshei mizbe'ach, when we're talking about something sanctified for the for
a קרבן. korban, אבל בקדשי בדק הבית, aval b'kodshei bedek habayis, but
if it's for the temple treasury, הקדיש תרנגולת, hikdish tarnagolet, if you
sanctified a chicken, מועלין בה וביצתה, mo'alin bah ubeitzatah, there's מעילה in
it and its egg. חמורה, chamora, if you sanctified a female donkey,
מועלין בה ובחלוה, mo'alin bah uvechalvah, in it and its milk. Now,
why did it all of a sudden jump to a female donkey?
You would have thought it said cow and so on. But this
is because there's a general assumption that or approach that if something
could be used as a קרבן, korban. you should not sanctify it
for בדק הבית. bedek habayis. So we didn't want to give an
example of sanctifying a pigeon for בדק הבית bedek habayis or a
cow for בדק הבית, bedek habayis, because those are things that could
be קרבן. korban. So we gave examples of things that could not
be קרבנות. korbanos. Now, why is there a difference between מזבח mizbe'ach
and בדק הבית? bedek habayis? Why by בדק הבית bedek habayis does
the stuff retain קדושה kedusha and not by מזבח? mizbe'ach. And the
difference is, and this is also a very important conceptual difference, so
there's some real key things here. One is the difference of לא
נהנין lo nehenin versus מעילה דרבנן. me'ilah derabbanan. The other is the
following that I said we discussed this before about the קדושה kedusha.
that's about ownership, which is about בדק הבית, bedek habayis, and a
קדושה kedusha, that's about sort of function and identity and where is
it going, which is the קדושה kedusha of a קרבן. korban Okay,
the essence of a קרבן korban when I sanctify it is not
that now the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash owns it. It's that this
now defines it as something that is going on the מזבח mizbe'ach.
and is directed towards מזבח mizbe'ach and so on. So with that
in mind, if I go ahead and I transfer title of my
of my cow herd to the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash or my
chickens to the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, well, what's the הלכה? When
the cows give milk and the chickens lay eggs, who owns them?
בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, they own it now. So if it's all
about ownership, they own it. So there's מעילה in them because that's
a קדושה kedusha that's about ownership. If I however sanctify my my
sheep for a קרבן korban and it gives milk, okay, so that
milk isn't going on the מזבח. mizbe'ach. The eggs of my pigeon
aren't going on the מזבח. mizbe'ach They're not the actual קרבן korban
itself, they're just a byproduct. So since they're not going on the
מזבח mizbe'ach and they're not the actual physical קרבן korban itself, there's
no מעילה by them. And this is the very important difference about
a קדושה kedusha, that's about where is it going and a קדושה
kedusha that's about ownership. And there's מעילה by both, but the focus
is different. And as this משנה mishnah points out, if it's about
ownership, the eggs are owned. If it's about where it's going, the
eggs aren't going on the מזבח. mizbe'ach. Yes.
So I have a I have a donkey I consecrate to the
בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Right. The donkey's pregnant, the donkey has has
baby, and and I have to milk the donkey.
We're going to discuss that. Oh, okay. So let's take a look
at the גמרא. Gemara. Okay. The גמרא Gemara says like this: אלא?
ella? Yeah.
You said that it you shouldn't sanctify an animal that could go
on the מזבח mizbe'ach. to the temple. Right. So how do we
get this case of the milk and the eggs?
Because we said we said milk of a donkey,
of a donkey,
and eggs of a chicken. Now, now the other thing you have
to understand is that normally there are really also two different concepts.
There's a concept called קדושת דמים kedushat damim and קדושת הגוף, kedushat
haguf, which is really what I was talking about. Is it about
ownership or is it about using the thing itself? There's another concept
which is called קדושת בדק הבית kedushat bedek habayit going to the
temple treasury and קדושת מזבח kedushat mizbe'ach going to the altar. Now
you would think that those are exactly the same. It's the other
two I just said, right? Yes, קדושת דמים kedushat damim is temple
treasury, מזבח mizbe'ach. is קדושת הגוף. kedushat haguf. But no, there are
ways in which you can have cross-categories. For example, if I sanctify,
if the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash needs some beams to build into
its ceiling and I sanctify a beam, that's actually a קדושת הגוף
kedushat haguf for בדק הבית. bedek habayit. It's going to be used
by the temple treasury, but it's the thing itself is going to
be used, not just for its its money. It's going to use
the thing itself. That's an example where it could be קדושת הגוף
kedushat haguf being used for the בדק הבית. bedek habayit. You could
have a קדושת דמים kedushat damim for the מזבח. mizbe'ach What would
be an example? Let's say I sanctify the קרבן korban an animal
with a מום. mum. Okay. What do I have to do with
that? I transfer it, I'm redeem it, and the money ultimately I
buy another קרבן korban. and that then is going to go for
for to the מזבח. mizbe'ach. Or I take a pile of money
and I say I'm sanctify this to use this money to buy
an עולה. olah. So I'm not going to bring the thing, the
money itself. That's a קדושת דמים למזבח. kedushat damim lemizbe'ach. Its value
is ultimately going to... it's not the thing itself, its value is
going to ultimately go to the מזבח. mizbe'ach? When we talk about
the difference in our משנה between the the eggs and the milk,
it's really not a question of מזבח mizbe'ach versus בדק הבית. bedek
habayit. It's really a question of are we dealing with קדושת הגוף
kedushat haguf or קדושת דמים? kedushat damim? Is it about the thing
itself or is it about its value, its cost, and therefore it's
about ownership? So that's what the גמרא Gemara focuses on. Let's read
the גמרא. Gemara.
They don't call it קדושת הגוף. kedushat haguf.
גוף. guf.
Yeah. Okay. Not enough for מעילה, but they have קדושת הגוף. kedushat
haguf. So the גמרא Gemara says like this: אלא גבי מזבח כי
אקדשיה קדושת דמים לאו אית ביה מעילה? ella gabei mizbe'ach ki akdeshah
kedushat damim lav it bei me'ilah? So the גמרא Gemara says so
one minute. Do you mean to tell me that that
one minute... let me just check for
one moment.
Right. So it says like this. So it says why did we
give the example that when you sanctified the תרנגולת, tarnegolet, the the
donkey and the and the chicken, that you're sanctifying it for בדק
הבית? bedek habayit? Let's say I sanctified my donkey and my chicken
for מזבח. mizbe'ach, Now how could I sanctify them for מזבח? mizbe'ach.
Well that would be an example of קדושת דמים למזבח. kedushat damim
lemizbe'ach. I'd have to transfer the קדושה kedusha and buy a קרבן.
korban, But I could in theory sanctify them למזבח, lemizbe'ach, but then
they'd have to get transferred. So the גמרא Gemara says like this.
So why did we give the example by the donkey and the
chicken that you gave it with בדק הבית? bedek habayit? Do you
mean to suggest that אלא גבי מזבח כי אקדשיה קדושת דמים לאו
אית ביה מעילה? ella gabei mizbe'ach ki akdeshah kedushat damim lav it
bei me'ilah? If you were to have sanctified the donkey and the
chicken for a קדושת דמים למזבח kedushat damim lemizbe'ach that there would
not be מעילה because why did you only give the example of
בדק הבית? bedek habayit? So אמר רב פפא חסורי מחסרא. amar Rav
Papa chisorei michasra. It's a bit hard to understand what exactly is
the גמרא. Gemara. Let's see the answer. הכי קתני. hachi katani. It's
missing some words. Here's what it means to say. במה דברים אמורים?
Bameh devarim amurim? By the case about the that the eggs and
the milk are not
מעילה, כשהקדיש קדושת הגוף לגבי מזבח. keshikdish kedushat haguf legabei mizbe'ach. So
this is a very special גמרא Gemara I would say, because often
these ideas are conflated, and it's rare that the גמרא Gemara is
very clear and distinct and saying that there's a difference between גוף
guf and דמים damim as opposed to מזבח mizbe'ach, and בדק הבית.
bedek habayit. So when is it that the eggs and the milk
is not מעילה? When it's קדושת הגוף למזבח, kedushat haguf lemizbe'ach, that
you're sanctifying the animals for going on the altar. אבל הקדיש קדושת
דמים לגבי מזבח. Aval hikdish kedushat damim legabei mizbe'ach. Let's say you
sanctified a donkey and a chicken, and but the money's ultimately for
an עולה. olah. So what you're going to have to do is
sell it and buy an עולה. olah. That's קדושת דמים למזבח. kedushat
damim lemizbe'ach. Eventually it's going to the מזבח, mizbe'ach, but right now
it's only a... not the thing itself, it's only about its cost.
So if you did that, נעשה כמי שהקדישו לבדק הבית. na'aseh kemi
shehikdisho lebedek habayit. For this purpose, it's the same as if you
gave it over to the temple treasury directly. And the הלכה would
be, הקדיש תרנגולת מועלין בה ובביצתה, חמור מועלין בו ובחלבו. hikdish tarnegolet
mo'alin bah uvveitzatah, chamor mo'alin bo uvchalavo. It applies to the eggs
and applies to the milk. Why? Because since right... because if it's
a קדושת דמים, kedushat damim, then right now it's basically not this
thing itself, it's about its its cost, it's about what you can
get for it. And therefore right now it's about an ownership idea.
So since it's about an ownership idea, even in the case where
It's going לגבי מזבח, legabi mizbe'ach, but at this stage it's not
that this that's going, it's about owning and therefore even the byproducts
are owned by the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and there is and
there is מעילה. Okay. Is that sort of clear? Now I will
say though that conceptually it is a little different. Because if I
מקדיש makdish something for an עולה, olah, my donkey for an עולה,
olah, it's not that it's owned by the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash.
It's still not owned by the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, right? They
can't come and say knock on my door, collect, hey we hear
you've got some עולה olah money, you know, please give it to
us. You know, I'm still bringing the קרבן, korban, right? So it
actually is conceptually interesting. Meaning the it's sort of like what do
they say? A cynic, he knows the price of everything and the
value of nothing, right?
So here it's all about the price. Even though it's not the
מקדש Mikdash collecting it. I'm going to be the one that's going
to use this donkey and sell it and take the proceeds and
buy an עולה. olah. It's about me me, not the בית המקדש,
Beis Hamikdash, but still it's not about the donkey. It's about the
price. And therefore since the concept of that קדושה kedusha is about
price and ownership, not about identity, so if the donkey produces milk,
so that's my property increasing in value. And that's the concept of
קדושה kedusha now is it's about the value of the thing and
the value increases. Whereas if I sanctified the sheep itself and the
sheep gives milk, then it's not about oh it's about the value
increasing. No, it's about the sheep. The sheep is going to the
מזבח. mizbe'ach. This stuff is not going to the מזבח, so it
doesn't have the same קדושה. kedusha Okay so I just want to
repeat that because you know I think that this as I said,
you know we haven't had a lot of גמרא Gemara today but
there was important conceptual issues and I just want to sort of
repeat them to make sure that we're clear. So let me just
take up two minutes to say everything we said today. So one
is we've been talking a lot about things that have to can't
get used, don't have מעילה. But it's important to remember that the
מסכת masechet began by saying that if there was let's say there
was a פסולא בקודש, psula bekodesh, if it became פסול in the
context of the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, in the context of the
עבודה, avodah, then it still has קדושה, kedusha there's still מעילה, you
still have to burn it, maybe because you have to burn it
and there's still a מצוה to burn it and so on. That's
פסולא בקודש. psula bekodesh. But if however it became unusable before any
of that happened, like a חטאת המתה chatas hameisah or a bird
that became too old or so on, then it's out of the
category. Or even if it was perfect in terms of the קדושה
kedusha and then it became unusable, like the bird that once was
fit and now is too old, the חטאת that once was good
and now is a חטאת המתה chatas hameisah or עולה olah that
died, so once was fit but now it's unusable and not a
פסולא בקודש, psula bekodesh, there's no מצות שריפה, mitzvas sreyfah, it died
and whatever, it's out and that type of case also the קדושה
is no longer considered purposeful and it's no מעילה. Point number one.
Point number two, bracketed we discussed a question about איסור הנאה issur
hana'ah versus מעילה דרבנן. me'ilah derabbanan איסור הנאה issur hana'ah is about
like חמץ chametz is אסור בהנאה. מעילה דרבנן me'ilah derabbanan is about
still a sense it's owned by the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, it
has קדושה, there was a taking away and therefore there has to
be a giving back, there has to be a payment. And then
there's a question at what times do we actually make an actual
מעילה דרבנן you know most of the time it's about an איסור
הנאה. issur hana'ah. The final thing, which is most important, is that
byproducts of the animal are not considered the animal itself and there's
no מעילה. That's things like the eggs and the and the and
the milk. However, blood is not considered a byproduct, that's considered the
animal itself, although blood in some ways is excluded, there are ways
it won't be excluded. And the final point, which is sort of
which is the very very important conceptual point in general when you
talk about קדושה and also when you talk about מעילה, is is
the קדושה that we're dealing with about the identity of the thing
or is it just about the value of the thing? קדושת הגוף
kedushas haguf is about identity, קדושת דמים kedushas damim is about value.
Those normally are linked but as we've seen not always the same
as where's it going. Is it going to the מזבח, then it's
about its identity. Is it going to the בדק הבית Bedek Habayis
and usually it's about the value, although you can have crossovers. And
what we basically said is when it's about value then when the
value increases it's still the קדושה extends to the increased value. If
it's about the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash owning it then obviously they
own the chicken they own the eggs. But even if it's about
me sanctifying my donkey to be used as a קרבן, since right
now the קדושה is about cost and value, it's not about identity,
when that value increases the קדושה extends to it. And therefore there's
going to be מעילה on the eggs, there's going to be מעילה
on the milk, even though that's not directly about the מקדש Mikdash
owning it, there's still a קדושה about value. And the only case
that that's not true is when it's not about value and the
בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash doesn't own it. So what are those cases?
קדושת הגוף kedushas haguf for the מזבח. That type of thing they
don't own it, it's not about value, it's about identity, and in
those types of things when it's not the thing itself, when it's
like the eggs or the milk, then there's no מעילה, there the
קדושה is only limited to the thing itself. Okay.